The first thing I want to do is go over our environment a little bit.
首先我们先大致浏览一下我们的开发环境
So now what we have is an index.html page,
目前我们有一个 index.html 页面
that's linked to a separate style.css page which is here.
它引入了一个单独的 style.css 页面样式
On the style.css, you can see we've set up our main grid.
在 style.css 中 你可以看到我们已经有了一个 grid
We've assigned our grid areas,
我们设置好了 grid area 属性值
and we've added a link to a second page which is post.html.
我们还添加了一个 link 标签链接到了另一个页面 post.html
If we follow that link in the browser,
如果我点击这个链接
we see it takes us to our second page which has a different layout,
你可以看到它会将我们带到另一个有着不同布局的页面
but also using CSS grid.
但是都是使用 CSS grid 实现的
This is using the html from post html,
这个页面的文件是 post.html
which links here to its own CSS page called blog.css.
对应的 CSS 样式文件是 blog.css
The CSS for that can be found here on blog.css,
我们可以在这里看到它的 CSS 内容
where you can see we've also set up our grid,
同样有一个 grid 容器
as well as our grid area.
以及对应的 grid area
Coming back to our homepage,
重新回到我们的主页
up until now, mostly what we've done is,
到目前为止 我们做的只是
we've stuck just these texts here inside of each element that makes up the grid.
简单的把一些文本放置在 grid 中的对应区域
But instead of just doing that, really,
但是除此之外
when you're programming for development,
当你正式开发项目时
what you're going do is you're going to nest elements inside of it.
你应该会在其中嵌套一些元素
So here we have our div class header box.
所以这里我们有一个 class 叫做 header box 的 div
So let's make a real header for a demo blog.
让我们来正式创建一个博客的头部
Let's say I want to make a blog about how beautiful nature is.
这里我们设置一个关于大自然有多美丽的标题
I might create an h1 tag that says,
我们放置一个 h1 标签
the beauty of nature brings us all home.
内容是 the beauty of nature brings us all home
That's a good blog title.
很不错的标题吧
Now you can see it's been replaced,
现在你可以看见
and we have our real-life header up here.
我们的标题已经出现了
Now, in the content,
再来看看内容区域
if we're talking about nature,
如果我们想讨论大自然的话
we probably want an image of nature.
我们可以放置一个关于大自然的图片
Now inside the div class content,
我们在 class 为 content 的 div 中
we're going to create an image tag,
创建一个图片标签
and we're going to set the source.
设置好 source 属性
If you see here I have put some images into a folder called images.
我已经在 images 文件夹里放置好了一些图片
So I can say images/waterfall jpeg,
所以我们可以直接使用 images/waterfall.jpeg 来引用它
and now we see a photo.
现在我们有了一张照片了
But, why is it so big?
但是 为什么图片这么大 ?
One of my favorite tricks for dealing with photos that
对于图片我比较喜欢的一个技巧是
css grid allows is instead of putting this as an image,
比起直接创建一个图片标签
element inside this element,
并放置在 css grid 元素中
because our grid has already set how big and how much space each element should take up,
由于 grid 中我们已经指定好了每个元素所占据的空间
we can actually come into the css,
我们可以直接进入到 css 文件中
and we can set the background image of the element to be that image.
设置元素的 background-image 属性
So the way we would do that is come to style.css,
所以这里我们打开 style.css 文件
and here in the content area,
在想要的
which is what we want,
content 区域中
I'm going to use the background image property,
设置 background-image 属性
which takes a path to the photo; images/waterfall.
指定好我们的图片路径为 images/waterfall
Now I'm going to say background size contain.
这里我们设置 background-size 为 contain 模式
So now we can see we have pictures of our beautiful waterfall.
好了 现在我们有了漂亮的瀑布图片了
There's another CSS property,
另外一个可以使用的
which we'll see if I can remember.
CSS 属性是
Background-repeat, no-repeat will just give us our one image.
background-repeat no-repeat 意思是图片不作重复处理
So we could also I believe, stretch this image.
我们也可以选择拉伸图片
But for us right now,
不过在这里
contain is really what we're looking for.
contain 已经足够了
So let's say we're on our blog homepage,
这是我们的主页
and we want to click to the most recent post.
我们可以点击 most recent post 链接
So now we're over to the html that is in post.html,
进入到我们的 post.html 页面
which is linked to blog.css.
它链接到 blog.css 文件
So this is where we have set out our grid template areas,
这里我们已经设置好了对应的网格区域
and as you can see in this one,
你可以看到
each grid template area has its own row.
每块区域都占据了独自的一行
So let's say that we wanted to be able to get
如果我们想要能够从第二个页面
back to our homepage once we're on the secondary page.
跳转回首页的话
We can go to post html and here,
我们可以打开 post.html 文件
in the footer box down at the bottom,
在底部的 footer box 区域内
we might want to say click here to go back to index.html.
我们可以添加一个指向 index.html 的链接标签
So now, we can easy get back to our blog homepage,
现在我们就可以很轻松的从首页
to our secondary layout,
跳转到第二个页面
and back to our first layout.
然后再跳转回第一个页面
This is an example of how you can build multiple page layouts using CSS grid.
这就是一个使用 CSS grid 搭建多个页面布局的例子